TheChaosLegion
I want to shine on you, and always like that dazzling sun.
I will defend you from all the darkness.
This is the truth from my heart.
If only our hearts could connect, I could get you to believe me.
Even if you can't see it now, don't lose it.
Your kindness won't be in vain.
You'll be carried aloft by the wind to somewhere that isn't here.
You'll cross the sea and cross time, and I know you'll blossom one day.
Whatever the day, I'll be there for you.
I hope I can watch over you like the sun for all time.
This is the truth from my heart.
～♪
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
（モン）
短槍(たんそう)使い！ 聞いているか！
Spear-wielder! Are you listening?
You won't get away
like you did before!
今度は いつぞやのようには
いかんぞ！
We'll do everything in our
power to bring you down!
総力を挙げて お前を倒す！
I don't know what your motive is,
dragging the prince around with you...
何が目的で皇子を
連れ回るのかは知らんが―
...but your work is done!
もう お前の役目は終わった！
Come out peacefully!
おとなしく姿を現せ！
Quiet, you noisy brats!
What's all this shouting about?
（トロガイ）
うるさい小僧どもが！
何を ぎゃあぎゃあ
わめいているんだい！
Wait a minute, isn't he...
（タンダ）あの人 確か…
Episode 20
To Hunter's Hole
（トロガイ）お前 星読み博士か？
You there. Are you a star reader?
（シュガ）はい トロガイ師
I am. Torogai, I wish that we had
had the chance to meet sooner.
できれば もっと早くに
一度お会いしておきたかった
フン！ 星読みとも思えん発言だね
That's the last thing I expected
to hear from a star reader.
お？ そうか
Ah, now I see.
It was you who had the second
queen write a letter to me, wasn't it?
二ノ妃(にのきさき)に わし宛の手紙を
書かせたのはお前かい？
いかにも
Indeed it was.
In that case, we might be able
to have a proper discussion.
なら ちょっとは
まともな話ができそうだ
若造の星読み博士よ
Young star reader, I want to hear
your thoughts on this matter.
ぜひ お前の考えを聞きたい
師匠？
Torogai?
Your prince has been made
the Nyunga Ro Chaga.
どうやら
ニュンガ･ロ･チャガとなった―
あの皇子様は
Apparently, when next year's
spring day of equality arrives...
来年の春の等しき日になると―
...he will set out for a place
called the land of feasting...
渡り鳥が 渡りを始めるように―
...just like a migratory bird
taking flight on its journey.
宴(うたげ)の地なる場所に
旅立ってしまうらしいのじゃ
しかも そのとき―
Also, I have learned that an egg-eater
will also come here from Nayug.
ナユグからは 卵食いも
やってくることが分かった
Egg-eater?
卵食い？
うむ
Just like a brown bear coming
to feast on toburya...
ちょうど産卵のために
川を上ってきたトブリャを―
...that are swimming
upstream to spawn.
ひぐまが食いに来るようにな
And according to Yakoo legends,
the guardian of the spirit...
そして 我らヤクーの
言い伝えによれば―
そのとき 精霊の守り人は
卵食いによって―
...is destined to be killed
by the egg-eater at this time.
殺される定めに あるらしいんじゃ
（ジン）皇子が死ぬだと？
You're saying that
the prince will die?
ああ そうじゃ
二度も言わせるな
Yes, that's what I'm saying!
Don't make me repeat myself!
What is the extent of your knowledge
regarding the Nyunga Ro Chaga?
実際 お前さんは―
どこまで ニュンガ･ロ･チャガに
ついての知識を持っている？
過去 精霊の守り人が―
Are there no stories about
the guardian of the spirit...
その定めから逃れたという
話はないのですか？
...escaping this fate in the past?
No, at least not in
Yakoo oral traditions.
少なくとも ヤクーの伝承にはない
Magic weaver of Yakoo...
ヤクーの呪術師よ
If what you say is true...
その話が本当だとしたら―
...is it not all the more reason
to turn the prince over to us?
なおさら 皇子を我らに
返したほうがよいのではないか？
I don't know what sort of
creature this "egg-eater" is...
その卵食いなるものが
何かは知らんが―
我らヨゴには 万を超す軍勢がいる
...but the army of Yogo is
in excess of 10,000 men.
Even if a demon like the one described
in the official history should appear...
たとえ 建国正史(けんこくせいし)に
書かれているような
魔物が現れたとしても―
我らなら
皇子を守ることは たやすい
...it will be a simple matter
for us to defend the prince.
ほう？
それが人には姿も見えず―
Will it still be a simple matter
if it's a monster from Nayug...
触ることすらできない
ナユグの怪物でもかい？
...that can be neither seen
or touched by human beings?
ナユグのモノにとっては―
To something from Nayug...
...the walls and spearmen surrounding
your palace won't mean a thing.
宮を取り囲む壁や
軍勢の槍(やり)ぶすまなど―
へとも感じんだろうさ
いくら皇子を隠そうと―
No matter how hard you try
to hide the prince, in the end...
最後はナユグから
その見えない爪で―
...it will reach out from Nayug with
its invisible claws and tear him apart.
皇子を いとも簡単に
引き裂いてしまうだろうよ
Knowing this, are you still telling me
that you'll be able to do anything...
それでも お前らに渡せば―
卵くらいは なんとか
してくれるってのかい？
...to stop the egg-eater
if we give him to you?
I have access to the epitaphs left
by the original master star reader.
私のもとには
初代聖導師(せいどうし)の残した碑文がある
If we can read and
decipher them, perhaps we...
それを読み解けば あるいは…
What the... You've had something
that important all this time...
なんだい
そんな大層なものがあるのに
いまだに読み解いておらんのか
...and you haven't
even read it all yet?
ヒビ･トナンの クソガキも
もうろくしたもんさ
That insolent whelp Hibi Tonan
must have gone senile.
This proves we can't hand over the
precious Nyunga Ro Chaga to that nitwit!
やはり そんな ぼんくらに―
大切なニュンガ･ロ･チャガを
渡すことはできないね！
（モン）では ヤクーなら
皇子を守れるというのか？
You're saying that the Yakoo
can protect him, then?
Of course!
当然じゃ！
（一同）う…
That's why the spear-wielder...
だからこそ短槍使いは―
...has already taken the
prince to a secret location.
皇子を すでに秘密の場所に
連れていったんだからね
（トロガイ）うそだと思うんなら
村中を探してみるがいいさ！
If you think I'm lying, feel free to
search the village from top to bottom.
But you must understand that she isn't
simply refusing to hand over the prince.
だが 短槍使いも皇子を
返さないと言ってるわけじゃない
It just means that she wants to
protect both the prince and the egg.
皇子も卵も
守りたいと言っているだけさ
お前らも
皇子を助けたいと思うんなら―
If you people want
to save the prince...
その碑文とやらを
さっさと読み解いて―
...go back and read
those epitaphs or whatever...
春の等しき日に
宴の地に来るがよい
...and come meet us at the land of
feasting on the spring day of equality!
We will be waiting for you there.
我らは そこで待っておる
（ジン）くだらん！
Enough of this! Prince Chagum
is our prince of Yogo.
チャグム皇子は 我らヨゴの皇子
貴様らヤクーの手を借りずとも―
We'll protect him ourselves!
We don't need help from you Yakoo!
我らが守ってみせる！
（トロガイ）ほう
Will you cut down
everyone in this village?
この村の者 全員を斬るか
それで この大地と皇子を
救えるんなら そうせい！
If you think that will save your
prince and this land, then do it!
だが 何も知らずに
皇子を連れ帰れば―
But if you blindly
return with the prince...
...the Nayug creature will
follow you to the palace.
ナユグのモノも宮に向かうぞ！
（シュガ）待て！
Wait! Pointless slaughter
will accomplish nothing here.
ここでむだな殺生をしても
意味がない！
Put away your swords!
刀をしまえ
Torogai, it would appear
that we star readers...
トロガイ師
どうやら 我ら星読みは―
ずいぶんと
つけあがっていたようだ
...have become quite
arrogant over the years.
やはり あなたたちと比べて
あまりに知識が不足している
Compared to your people,
our knowledge is sorely lacking.
（トロガイ）そこの者たちは
そうは思っては おらんようだぞ
Your men don't seem to
be of the same opinion.
For now, I will leave
this place with my men.
今は この者たちと共に
この場を去ろう
（一同）う…
（シュガ）だが―
But by the time of the
spring day of equality...
春の等しき日までに 必ず
皇子を救う方法を携え戻ってくる
...I will find a way to save Prince
Chagum, and we will surely return here.
When we do, I expect that you
will return Prince Chagum to us!
そのときは
皇子を我らに返してほしい
Master Shuga!
シュガ様！
（シュガ）黙れ！
Silence!
You tried with all your might, and
still you couldn't kill this bodyguard.
お前たちが息精張っても
討てなかった用心棒だ
春までは
女用心棒に皇子を託すのが―
Entrusting the prince to her until
spring is the safest course of action.
最も確実な手段
Jin, perhaps what
Master Shuga says is right.
ジン 確かにシュガ様の
言うとおりかもしれん
For now, put away your sword.
ここはいったん 剣を収めろ
呪術師よ
皇子は息災であらせられるか？
Magic weaver,
is His Highness in good health?
うむ…
In that case, Torogai, let us meet
again in the land of feasting next spring.
トロガイ師
では来春 宴の地にて
お会いしましょう
そちは トロガイ師の弟子か？
Are you Torogai's apprentice?
That's right...
Thank you for your
assistance that day.
あのときは 世話になった
カマキリの卵の話がきっかけで
私は今ここにいる
Your information regarding mantis
eggs was the key that led me here.
感謝している
I am grateful.
We haven't a moment to lose.
もはや一刻の猶予もない
宮に帰りしだい
碑文解読役を組織せねばなるまい
As soon as we
return to the palace...
...I must organize a team
to read through the epitaphs.
He remembered me. I'm surprised.
覚えていたのか 俺のこと
You've met that star reader before?
お前 あの星読みと
会ったことがあるのか？
Yes, once. On the outskirts
of Ogi no Shimo.
ええ 一度 扇(おうぎ)の下(しも)のはずれで
ほう
にしても 師匠―
I have to admit, Torogai...
...I'm amazed you managed to
come up with a lie like that on the spot.
よくとっさに
あんな うそがつけましたね？
フン バルサが戻りしだい
狩穴に向かうぞ
Once Balsa gets back,
we'll set out for Hunter's Hole.
Are you sure that
you can't stay here?
（ソウヤ）やはり ここに
残るわけには いかんのですか？
Thank you, but no.
（バルサ）ありがとうございます
ですが―
There are certain preparations
that I want the boy to make.
この子に いろいろと準備を
させてやりたいこともありますので
（ソウヤ）そうですか…
I see.
世話になったな
Thank you for helping us.
We have no intention of
spending the winter idly.
我らとて ただ手をこまねいたまま
冬を越す気はない
ニュンガ･ロ･チャガのことは
任せておけ
Leave the Nyunga Ro Chaga to us.
（ソウヤ）よろしくお願いします
We are all counting on you.
（トロガイ）うむ
（ニムカの母）これは ニムカが
採ってきた シクルの蜜です
This is shikul honey
that Nimka collected.
Please enjoy it while you
are holed up in the cave.
穴ごもりのときに 皆さんで
（チャグム）ありがとう
Thank you.
Please take care.
（ニムカ）どうか お元気で
では そろそろ行ってみます
All right, we should get going.
お気をつけて
Be careful.
What's this? They're seeing us off?
何じゃ？ 見送りか？
何のために 頭を下げるんだ？
What are they bowing for?
誰かが 背負わねばならぬ運命を―
They do it to show their
respect toward the one...
...who shoulders the destiny
that someone had to bear.
１人で背負った者への
敬重の念からじゃ
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
（馬方）どう どう！
Whoa!
（シュガ）シュガに ございます
It is Shuga.
ガカイ様 いらっしゃいますか？
Master Gakai, are you there?
Master Shuga?
（星読み）シュガ様
あ… ガカイ様は ただいま…
Master Gakai is currently...
（ガカイ）かまわん 入れ
It's all right. Come in.
失礼いたします
Pardon the interruption.
（ガカイ）何用だ？
What do you want?
（シュガ）ガカイ様のお力を
お借りしたく 伺いました
I have come because
I wish to ask for your help.
With Crown Prince Sagum dead...
（ガカイ）サグム皇太子が
亡くなられた今―
カシヅキとしての職も失った
...I have been removed from
my post of tutor-governor.
While you, on the other hand...
それにひきかえ お前は―
...now hold authority on par with
the master star reader himself.
今や 聖導師様と並ぶほどの
実権を持つと聞く
フッ 何なりと申しつけたらどうだ
That being the case,
why not simply give me an order?
After all, I have no right to refuse.
私に断る権限など ないのだからな
Master Gakai,
I traveled to Toumi village.
ガカイ様
私はトウミ村に赴き
星読みの持つ知識が―
There, I learned to my chagrin...
ヤクーの知に 遠く及ばないことを
思い知らされました
...that star readers' knowledge pales
in comparison to that of the Yakoo.
Nevertheless, we must now
surpass even their knowledge.
ですが 我らは
その知識を上回らねばならない
That doesn't concern me.
（ガカイ）私には関係ないことだ
I beg to differ.
This concerns not only Shin-Yogo...
いいえ！
これは
我が新ヨゴ皇国のみならず―
...but everyone who lives
on the Nayoro peninsula!
ナヨロの地に住む者すべてに
関係することなのです！
Master Gakai, do me
the honor of assisting me...
ガカイ様！
どうか 碑文解読の
長(おさ)になっていただき―
私に お力をお貸しください！
...by taking charge of our
epitaph-deciphering efforts!
ガカイ様は
あらゆる学問に精通し―
You are conversant in
every field of knowledge...
探究心の深い お方
...and you possess a
deeply inquisitive mind.
Only one man is capable of keeping
this project running smoothly!
この仕事を 滞りなく
進めることができるのは―
Master Gakai, that man is you!
ガカイ様をおいて
他には ありません！
ここいらは
光扇京(こうせんきょう)よりも寒いから―
This area is colder
than it is in Kosenkyo...
...so the leaves
change color much earlier.
紅葉する時期が ずっと早いんだ
He's been like that
ever since we left Toumi.
トウミを出てから
ずっと あんな感じだな
Yes, but at least we're
almost at Hunter's Hole.
ああ けど とりあえず
狩穴はもうすぐだ
チャグムのことは
それから考えるさ
We'll worry about Chagum
after we get there.
（タンダ）そうだな
True.
まったく しばらく
ほっとくだけで すぐ このザマだ
I swear, you leave this place vacant
for a while and look what happens.
Torogai and I made
a few improvements...
（タンダ）
岩の下にできた空洞に―
...in the cavern here
beneath the rock.
師匠と俺とで
少しばかり手を入れたんだ
今 明かりを入れてくる
Wait here. We'll go light some fires.
（バルサ）ジグロ 帰ってきたよ
Jiguro...
I'm back.
Okay, we've got some lights going!
Try making your way down.
（タンダ）明かりをつけたぞ
下りてきてごらん
I have to get him to hold
his head high like he used to.
あの背中が前のように しゃんと
するようにしてやらなきゃね
Surprised? We call this part
of the cave the entry hall.
（タンダ）驚いたか？
俺たちは ここを
玄関って呼んでいるんだ
But it's too open and cold out here,
so we set up the rooms further in.
でも ちょっと広すぎて
寒いから 奥に部屋が作ってある
おいで
Follow me.
The hole on the right extends so far that
it's like a maze, so don't go in there.
右の穴は奥が深すぎて
迷路になっているから―
入っては ダメだ
There's a spring in the middle one.
The one on the left is our home.
（タンダ）真ん中は泉が湧いている
左が 我が家だ
ここが居間だ
This is the living room.
向こうは 動物の肉なんかを
くん製にする部屋
Over there is a room where
we smoke meats or whatever.
あっちは 食料と水の貯蔵庫だ
Over there is the storehouse
for supplies and water.
There doesn't seem to be
any obvious damage.
どうやら
目立った傷みは ないようじゃな
This place never changes, does it?
ここは変わりませんね
Every last detail is
exactly like it was.
何もかも昔のままだ
This is the first time I've been
back here since Jiguro died.
ジグロが死んでからは
一度も来ていなかったけど
We'll be penned in here
once it starts snowing.
（トロガイ）雪が降り始めたら
身動きできなくなっちまう
There's a lot that we
need to see to before then.
その前に
やっとくことは山ほどある
さっそく 冬ごもりの
準備に入るとしよう
We need to get ready to
hole up for the winter right away.
You give it a try too.
（バルサ）お前も やってごらん
If we don't prepare them like this,
they won't smoke properly.
こうやって処理しないと
うまく くん製にできないからね
さて お茶でも入れるか
Okay, I think I'll go
make us some tea.
フゥ…
これが済んだら 早めに寝るよ
Once we're done with these,
we'll turn in early.
We're going out first thing
in the morning to set traps.
あしたは 早くに
わなを仕掛けに行くからね
分かった
All right.
You clean it just like
you would a hare.
やり方は
野ウサギなんかと一緒だ
Give it a try on your own.
１人で やってごらん
（バルサ）ここも だいぶ
いっぱいに なってきたじゃないか
This place is pretty much full.
これなら十分 冬を越せそうだ
This should be more than enough
to keep us fed through winter.
タンダ 虫こぶはあるかい？
Tanda, do you have
any insect galls?
I want to tan some hides.
皮を なめしたいんだ
Sure.
I'm going to borrow this
mortar and pestle too.
（バルサ）こっちの鉢と
すりこぎも借りるよ
Go ahead.
バルサ これで足りるか？
Balsa, is this enough?
That'll be plenty. Thank you.
（バルサ）十分さ ありがとよ
It looks to me like that boy
has toughened up quite a bit.
あの小僧も だいぶ たくましく
なってきたようじゃないか
バルサの しごきにも
耐えてるみたいだしね
He's enduring
Balsa's tough training too.
（タンダ）口数が少ないのが
気になりますけどね
True, but I'm worried that
he hardly ever says anything.
そればっかりは
本人が答えを出すしかないのさ
He has to work that
through on his own.
わしらが いくら口を出しても―
We can try to talk to him as
much as we want, but in the end...
結局 ニュンガ･ロ･チャガの
運命を引き受けるのは―
...it's the boy who has to accept
the fate of the Nyunga Ro Chaga.
あの小僧なんだからね
（チャグム）痛っ
ん？ どうした
What's the matter?
Let me see.
見せてごらん
あかぎれだね
Your hand is chapped.
待ちな 薬を塗ってやる
Wait, I'll put some salve on it.
我慢しな
Hang in there. This medicine
might sting, but it works wonders.
この薬は しみるけど
ちゃんと効くからね
私も お前くらいのときは
よく あかぎれを こさえたもんさ
Back when I was your age,
my hands were rubbed raw a lot too.
そのたびに ジグロが
この薬を塗ってくれた
And every time, Jiguro rubbed
this salve on them for me.
He was usually very strict...
ふだんは厳しかったけど―
不思議と あかぎれになったときは
優しかったね
...but whenever my hands were chapped,
he became gentle for some reason.
ジグロというのは
バルサを育ててくれた人のことか？
This Jiguro person...
Was he the man who raised you?
ああ 育ての親で 命の恩人さ
Yes, he was my foster father,
and the man I owe my life to.
命の恩人？
The man you owe your life to?
Right.
Come to think of it, I never
did tell you about him, did I?
そういえば お前には
ちゃんと話したことがなかったね
If it weren't for Jiguro,
I probably wouldn't be here today.
ジグロがいなかったら 今頃
私は ここにいなかったろうよ
間違いなく
６歳のときに殺されていたからね
I would have been killed
when I was six, no question.
Will you tell me about him?
その人の話 聞かせてくれないか？
そうか…
今が話すときかもしれないね
You know, maybe this is
the right time to tell you.
私の生まれたカンバルって国は―
As you know,
my homeland of Kanbal...
...is a small country that lies
beyond the Misty Blue Mountains.
知ってのとおり 青霧(あおぎり)山脈を
越えた所にある小国でね
そんな所でも―
Even in a place like that, people
constantly want to start conflicts.
人は絶えず 争い事を
起こしたがるものなんだ
As I sat huddled and alone, holding back the tears on those nights...
When it felt like I was about to succumb to my doubts...
...there you were, at my side before I knew it.
It was none other than you who was there for me.
I keep wishing, "I want to be strong." I stumble and hurt myself again.
But because I have you to believe in, I can get back to my feet.
I simply want to tell my dear one, "Thank you."
At the top of my lungs, again and again.
I call out to my precious loved one.
Is my voice reaching you?
In this world that always changes, human warmth never does.
I'm certain I sensed the presence of the one that I hold dear.
～♪
Next Time
With pleading eyes,
he begged his friend.
"Look after my daughter," he said.
Next time, "Jiguro Musa."
Episode 21
Jiguro Musa
Why did I quit the King's Spears?